<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>An avenue of ways</title>
    <description>Musings on life, technology and audio.
</description>
    <link>http://willemave.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://willemave.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 16:07:14 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 16:07:14 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>

      <item>
        <title>Book  ray dalio principles</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-progress-ray-dalio-principles&quot;&gt;[In Progress] Ray Dalio Principles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Not knowing taught me more than knowing”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we have common principles? Are we clear about them? Do we write them down?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can bootstrap their principles from Parents, Religion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray’s Principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q: Does social media provide a fuzzy look into peoples principles?
&lt;em&gt;“Strive for a lot and fail well - learn but don’t get knocked out“…“How do I know I’m right? Curiosity about why other peoples are different.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like Munger’s Mental Models, main focus of helping against inherent decision bias?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistakes:
&lt;em&gt;“Decision making is learned”&lt;/em&gt; - disagree, there are many human biases that drive decision making.
&lt;em&gt;“While everyone assumes the future is a modified version of the present, it most likely is not”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Better make sense of other people, or other teams or places”…”Most everything has happened before for logical cause and effect reasons”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go really deep - Ray’s story about understanding the complete grain + meat + livestock map was super detailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Always assume you’re missing something”&lt;/em&gt; - we deal with lots of complex systems! Break things down into simpler Machines that you can model (chicken is a small machine that eats feed, so lock in feed future prices).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you determine of you want, figure out the relative importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debate opinions with smart people with differing opinions.
Know when not to have an opinion
System wide principles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change can only happen if you admit what you’re not good at. There is almost a good path in a case where you need two things and have to choose.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/12/12/Book-Ray-Dalio-Principles/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/12/12/Book-Ray-Dalio-Principles/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  selections of</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-progress-selections-from-science-and-sanity&quot;&gt;[In Progress] Selections from Science and Sanity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are organisms that abstract, meaning is context driven and terms are multi-ordinal. Language allows for passing down culture and knowledge and therefore ‘time binding’, it is a function of the brain, as in derived from language. Limitations of language (representations), all statements probable in varying degrees.
Generalizations on civilization started with insufficient data (animal behaviors vs man behaviors). Infantilism still prevails, still primitive semantics, technology seems to accelerate these primitive behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/12/09/Book-Selections-of/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/12/09/Book-Selections-of/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  sapiens</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-progress-sapiens&quot;&gt;[In Progress] Sapiens&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the underdogs, many other predators have had millions of years of improvement, majestic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard to have both intestines and brains as they take lots of energy, fire help optimize this. Fire was strong leverage against other animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we a product of inter-breeding (homosapiens vs other Neanderthals?) Or was it more a geonocide. DNA testing shows some inter-breeding. Could be cleansing, could have ran out of resources, etc. Interesting. What if they still lived now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 70k years ago we started winning for the previous 30k we lost quite a bit vs the Neanderthals. What was different about our language? Was it gossip-theory, the mental capability to talk behind peoples backs is enourmous. Myths help align us (religion). 150 is the size of a “gossip group”. A company is ‘legal fiction’, can pay taxes but isn’t a thing, LLC (or Corporation) is a great invention, same with joint-stock-options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagined realities are not lies. Everyone believes in. Dual reality, the real physical reality, and the imagine reality becomes stronger (actually now sustains the physical, vs wildlife reserves). Allows for really quick evolutions in our social contracts or behaviors. Do stories that are passed down allow us to iterate faster than DNA being passed down?Trade is based on Imagined Realities. IR became Culture, culture became history. In small groups were similar to chimps. Tools are no use unless we can collaborate, more complex the tool the more collaboration (nuclear warheads are 1000s). Fiction and myths allows us to levels these up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6-70k+ years ago. Ancient hunter gathers were much more diverse, eating many things, being a master of their domain. Religion and political structure is murky for these humans. Have we been the same level of violent (5% back then and same in 2000’s, bands being genocide). Isolated in AfroAsian. Indonesians ‘evolved’ boats, went to Australia, sapiens extinct most flora there - we’re ecological serial killers, mammoths, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/26/Book-Sapiens/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/26/Book-Sapiens/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  radical candor</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;radical-candor&quot;&gt;Radical Candor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GSD, listen to ideas, listen to each other, clarify, debate, decide, persuade, learn from results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quiet listen, vs strong listening - make a case and make sure to invite argument. Don’t want a tyrant if the most verbose.
Clarify&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure to not squash ideas early, help people develop then,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selection, elimination, emphasis
Debate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have someone debate other side&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check ego at door&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on factseperate debate vs decide, add when to resolve by to close things out
Decide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facts not recommendations when having to decide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to the source&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ok to spelunk - asked others it’s not ok to stay high level all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Address audience emotions, show the path to logic and credibility, know details layers deep
Execute
Learn from results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Denial is much stronger than learning, pressure to be consistent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools
Relationships
Care about yourself, essence of leadership is not getting overwhelmed by circumstances, fullest best self to work.
Relinquish unilateral control
Avoid the invisible man, “you guys”
Booze is dangerous, sometimes best event is time back for themselves
Emotions are just as contagious as germs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical Candor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave the unimportant things unsaid each day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up down and across&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Care personally &amp;amp; challenge directly: it’s not mean it’s clear.  Easier to challenge internally who they are than externally what they’ve done&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruinois empathy does not cause you to build relationships that you can leverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go as deep with praise as with criticis,make sure you have details and understand all aspects.  Same level of dedication to both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy to move from obnoxious aggression to manipulative incenserity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture of guidance, praise and criticism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand everyone to keep them from burn out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drive results collaboratively, we vs I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell me the critical success factors of the existing incumbents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an hour to solve a problem spend 55 minutes to find it and five minutes Solving it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t conflate a job to be done with an institution doing the job&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth vs stable employees, 2axis graph, part performance vs growth desire.  Just working for a paycheck is totally fine. My job is not too instill purpose in people but understand them deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance - how long have you spent thinking about the praise, the criticism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humble and helpful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Criticize privately, Praise publicly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t challenge internal essence only external behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confidence in abilities, but say the work is not good enough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Problem is not due to some unsolvable personality flaw”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highly accomplished people you may have to goto extended to get through&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Just say it”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to see if you ruinously empathetic or obnoxious aggression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring your whole self to work. Can’t successfully hide your emotions, own up to how you feel. Bad emotions are like a flu. You can’t control emotions, react compassionately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledge emotions, shortcut to heart of matter “i can see your mad”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask questions, keep listening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Don’t be sad” “Don’t be mad” is totally the wrong approach&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s fine to say “I need to step out and grab some water” if you can’t handle it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidance
Praise and Criticism, get from, give to and encourage between.
How can you get criticism from the team? Criticize myself publicly.  Criticize in private does not apply to bosses.  Good reaction to public criticism builds trust.  Go to Question: “is there anything that I can or stop doing that would make it easier to work with me”.  Embrace the discomfort, get a real response, repeat it, or say “You have a reputation for giving great feedback”. Never criticize the criticism, manage your feelings.  If you don’t agree, find something you do, check your understanding, repeat what you heard, and that you want to think about it. Then explain why you can’t change or disagree. Gauge the guidance, if it’s all good, it’s bs.
Management fix it week, beaurcracy bugs, management bug tracking system.
Be Humble:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Situation, Behavior, Impact. Praise and Criticism.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Left Handle Column (avoid arrogance): Write down what you said in right hand column, what you thought in left hand column. Look back on what you thought. Subjective experience is not objective truth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stating intention to help can help. Show don’t tell, show what is good or bad, don’t retreat to abstractions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make an introduction if someone else needs help.
Just because you can’t solve it, doesn’t mean you shouldn’t offer guidance.
Don’t delay.
Impromptu Guidance. Don’t just schedule a meeting, say it right away in between a meeting (3-5 minutes max), do it consistently. Unspoken criticism blows up. Don’t black hole effort.
Emotional weight is a quick praise after something. Follow up with email is a lasting thing.
Praise in public, criticize in private. Praise is for them, some people don’t like public praise.&lt;br /&gt;
Don’t personalize, care personally. Use SBI. “Your wrong -&amp;gt; I think that’s wrong”.
Praise / Criticism stickers on the Radical Candor framework - ask team to rate me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Grove: Listen, Challenge, Commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender bias and being radically candor is harder because it’s politicized. Never stop challenging directly. Care personally, but kill the angel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formal Performance reviews can clarify - reinforces feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solicit peer review first, perhaps clarify the feedback that people provide about others. Write things down - protect against ruinous empathy. Identify set of things to work on and check in on them during 1:1’s. Never let another person complain about someone else, have them work it out together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whale / Monkey exercise at retro’s?
Killer Whale - extraordinary work
Whoops the Monkey - who made a mistake&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immunity to talk about mistakes - the FAA does this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking truth to power: Skip level meeting: Most people don’t want to criticize the  boss is not guilty.  Explain it, show it, explain it again. Have the line managers explain it to their directs. Don’t only do when there are problems, this is not “for attribution” meeting. Take notes yourself. Start with praise, better, then sucks. Format and send out notes directly. Then follow up with concrete actions. Ask to see if people feel the changes, if not manager needs to goto IC. If you can change one thing? Does this resonate with you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the two core principles: (1) Am I showing my team that I care personally, and  (2) Am I challenging each person directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Career conversation, Businesses can’t care personally. Care personally axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand peoples motivations and dreams - balance growth and trajectory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;18 month plan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crazy ass dream? What skill do you need to reach your dream?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is your life story (what motivations)
Life Story, from kindergarten to today. Get to know what people cares about. Have managers try with each other to practice. Much better than abstract concepts of “financial independence”.
Understand Dreams. framing is better than 5 year plan or next “level” - can lead to awkward conversations.&lt;br /&gt;
What do you want your pinnacle career like look like? 3-5 different dreams, write these down as columns, then add skills needed to reach these as rows and what level of competence. Dreams are aligned with core values (life story).
18 month plan.  Focus on what skills, clarify them and align with current work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth Management. Challenge directly axis.
Put names in boxes, rock stars (what they need to be productive) and super stars (projects to stretch super stars), performing poorly but can improve (wrong roles, expectations clear), can’t improve (PIP, etc).  3-5 bullet point growth plan for each employee. 5-15 minutes per direct on these bullet points. Correlate these quadrants and growth points for across teams, make sure people are treating super / rock stars appropriately. Make sure not to just think that your directs are super / rock, this causes leadership. Don’t let leaders ride on the excellent work of those underneath them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiring / Firing / Promotions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define team fit as, define culture in 3 - 4 words, define growth trajectory.
No assholes, if not nice to recruiter, or someone else, don’t hire.
If we’re not dying to hire someone, bias towards no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips:
Tolerating bad work is unfair to people doing great work.
After firing someone,fFollow up a few months after letting someone go.
Calibrate all the promotion packets across the teams.
Avoid status, i.e. announcing a promotion via emails. Focus not the work, not the status.
(Partnership, Absentee, Micro) management, do partnership, don’t do the others.
Take a moment to say thanks, not thank you for the merchants, make it personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:1 - Move up on the care personally meeting. Mindset, get to know them. Basic expectations for agenda (structured or not). Identify gaps. Why? How can I help? What keeps you up at night? What are you working on that you don’t want to? Why? What are you not working on that you want to? Why? What can you do to start? How do you feel about priorities of dependent teams?  Have you talked to those teams? What happened?  Encourage new ideas during 1:1 - help them clarify, nurture the ideas. What do you need to further develop? Can you explain it again? Is it that their to stupid to understand, or not clear on it? If it’s just updates / good news, as for bad news.
Staff -
Think Time
Debating meetings
Decision meetings
All Hands&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Radical-Candor/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Radical-Candor/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  payoff hidden logic that shapes our motivations</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;payoff-hidden-logic-that-shapes-our-motivations&quot;&gt;Payoff hidden logic that shapes our motivations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long list of incentives, what does your motivation equation look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivation includes elements not related to joy, it often drives us to achievements that are difficult, painful, challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivations to conquer helplessness and maintain control of our lives are strong.  Things that give us meaning don’t necessarily make us happy. Big difference between happiness and meaning, sit on a beach for ever may be blissful but boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“human motivation is actually based on a time scale that is long, sometimes even longer than our lifetimes.”…”beyond our social circle…our existence”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-destroy-motivation&quot;&gt;How to Destroy Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Meaningful” - building something and have satisfaction from it
“Sisyphus” - Loss of something that is built (push boulder up a hill to have it roll back down) - this crushed meaning even for people who love doing the task.
Acknowledgement goes a long way to create a meaningful outcome. Even if the work product doesn’t launch, don’t destroy, what parts can be re-used, what can we learn, what can be applied anywhere else?
We have to use intuition every time we don’t have sufficient data. “when trying to intuit the outcome of these different conditions, participants predicted that the effect of meaning would be much smaller than it actually was. They greatly underestimated the power of meaning.”
When motivation crumbles it’s not just the project, but all your life choices during and up to that project that are crumbled, including longer-term dreams.
— does our clinically sterile environment show people that they’re replaceable? Do constant seating shuffles re-enforce this?
If work is boring, try to change mental framing.  How is the work I’m doing helping someone down the road? What meaning can I find here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;joy-of-making-something&quot;&gt;Joy of making something&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“IKEA effect”, cake mix boxes initially had fewer steps, sold poorly.
We all have egocentric bias for things we create, in economic terms we over value our products based on market value.
When you layer in identity
If you can execute on your idea, it’s much more powerful vs, just implementing someone else’s.
“The lesson here is that a little sweat equity pays us back in meaning—and that is a high return.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#3 money, pizza, compliments
Motivating is impossible to determine explicitly. Difference between, UN, NBA and a start-up. Motivations (pizza vs compliment vs money) cause different performance characteristics in the days after.
managers need to take into account (and measure) not only the direct effect of different incentives but also their delayed and enduring outcomes. The more a company can offer employees opportunities for meaning and connection, the harder those employees are likely to work and the more enduring their loyalty is likely to.
findings suggest that when we are in the midst of a task, we focus on the inherent joy of the task, but when we think about the same task in advance, we overfocus on the extrinsic motivators, such as payment and bonuses. This is why we are not good predictors of what will motivate us and what will crush our motivation.
not at work, we don’t consider most relationships to be in the fixed-pie category. Instead, most of our relationships fall into an expanding-pie category. Doesn’t take much to move into the expanding pie category
good relationships aren’t transactional;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously there are efficiency gains from decomposing with into components. However substantial motivation can stem from meaning and personal investment which is antithetical to deep specialization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodwill: sometimes you can kill it with measuring or rewarding the wrong thing. Good will and Trust is a necessary part of motivation to go beyond. Contacts and lawyers statements of low probability can erode trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#4 death.
What if everything was erased the second you died? That would destroy motivation really quickly, extreme version of Sisyphus test.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Payoff-hidden-logic-that-shapes-our-motivations/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Payoff-hidden-logic-that-shapes-our-motivations/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  munger</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;charlie-munger-the-complete-investor&quot;&gt;Charlie Munger The Complete Investor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from the success and failure of others is the fastest way to get smarter and wiser without a lot of pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the benefit of creating a checklist is the process of writing down your ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Treat a share of stock as a proportional ownership of the business. 2. Buy at a significant discount to intrinsic value to create a margin of safety. 3. Make a bipolar Mr. Market your servant rather than your master. 4. Be rational, objective, and dispassionate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because investing is a probabilistic activity, decisions made in ways that are fundamentally sound may sometimes produce bad results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;three baskets: in, out, and too tough. … We have to have a special insight, or we’ll put it in the “too tough” basket.value investing system is intentionally designed to underperform an index in a bull market;borrowed from algebra is that many problems are best addressed backward. For example, by avoiding stupidity, a person can often discover what he or she wants through subtraction. By eliminating the stupid paths that one can take in life, a person can find the best way forward, even given inevitable risk, uncertainty, and ignorance.The average performance of all investors has to be the average performance of all assets. It’s a zero-sum game if you judge it relative to the market.value investors spend most of their time reading and thinking, waiting for significant folly to inevitably raise its head.Can you understand and implement the principles to make the required choices about value investing variables?Munger believes the place to start is at the bottom, with business fundamentals, and work up. What does the company sell and who are its customers and competitors? What are the key numbers that represent the value the business generates? The list of important questions that an investor must answer is extensive.stay away from making predictions about how cash flows will change in the future based on projections and forecasts. What Munger looks for is a business that has a significant track record of generating high, sustained, and consistent financial returns. If valuing the business requires understanding how cash flows will change in the future based on factors like rapid technological change, Munger puts that business in the too hard pile and moves on to value other companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;valued like baseball cards is a loser’s game because it requires that you predict the behavior of often irrational and emotional herds of human beings. A Graham value investor puts short-term predictions about mass psychology in the too hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you do not follow the business to value the stock approach, in the view of Graham value investors, you are a speculator and not an investor..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;do not spend any time looking at technical charts of stock price movements,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Maynard Keynes defined speculation as “the activity of forecasting the psychology of the market.” 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;your data about the present is extensive while your data about the future will always be zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;best way to determine the value of a business is based on the price a private investor would pay for the entire business. For example, Seth Klarman determines the price he would pay for the asset in question and calls that the private market value.  private market intrinsic valuation for a Graham value investor requires that the asset generate free cash flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Munger does not own gold as an investment because it is impossible to do a bottom-up fundamental valuation, because gold is not an income-producing asset.
#3
Intrinsic value is the present value of future cash flows. Margin of safety reflects the difference between the intrinsic value and the current market price.objective as a Graham value investor is to buy a share of stock at a sufficiently large bargain that you do not need to predict short-term price movements in the stock market.margin of safety principle is the simple idea that having a cushion in terms of excess value can protect you against making an error.
believes in a mostly efficient hypothesis. He believes that the difference between mostly and always efficient is a huge opportunity for a Graham value investor. Stocks are sometimes underpriced and sometimes overpriced. Anyone who invested through the Internet bubble (as I did) and who still thinks that markets are always efficient (a so-called extreme view of market efficiency) is bonkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Market’s bipolar nature is his gift to Graham value investors. Occasionally he will present them with great bargains. At other times he’ll buy your assets at a premium. Munger’s point on this is simple: do not treat Mr. Market as wise; instead, view him as your servant. It is certain that the prices of investment assets will wiggle above and below intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groucho Marx joke: you do not want to hire an investment manager that would take you for a client!
#4
building blocks in a step-by-step process and employ techniques like checklists, which reinforce the Graham value investing system, you can avoid making most mistakes—or at least making new mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worldly Wisdom
you can’t really know anything if you just remember isolated facts and try and bang ’em back. If the facts don’t hang together on a latticework of theory, you don’t have them in a usable form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple models needed to avoid seeing the world in one way “when all you have is a hammer” come from psychology, history, mathematics, physics, philosophy, biology…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People weigh models with numbers higher because of stats, but  a single model that is precisely wrong, is worse than many partially correct harder to measure models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because life is related, so are models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn from others, makes no sense to sit down and dream it all up ourselves.  “Munger reads hundreds of biographies, to see how people think”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have dysfunctional decision-making heuristics from psychology caused an error? Are there approaches one can use to find those mistakes? use a model from algebra and invert problems to find a solution. Double-check on decision, match result against many different models, be consistently less stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism means that people will try to replicate any profitable business, this is why moats are important, you have an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;If you cannot explain why you failed after making a mistake, it was too complex of a (business&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;project&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;etc)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychology of Human Misjudgment
Investing is less than a zero sum game.  Dysfunctional decision making and emotional errors can be an opportunity
Reward and Punishment Superresponse Tendency - Incentives are everything.  “Skin in the game”
Liking/ Loving Tendency - One check is to seek out people who disagree with you. Should change one idea per year.
Disliking/ Hating Tendency - separate how you feel about one thing from the other. I.e. not liking someone because of the school they went to.
Doubt-Avoidance Tendency - don’t let history cloud having doubt about something, doubt is a healthy check.
Inconsistency-Avoidance Tendency - get’s worse as you’ve invested more, even worse with doubt-avoidance.
Curiousity Tendency - too much info, or too many products, all about tradeoffs
Kantian Fairness Tendency - unfair for individual but fair for group, investors can be irrational here, Navy if captain runs ship aground still his fault even if it isn’t fair
Envy/ Jealousy Tendency - someone will always be getting richer than you, who cares?
Reciprocation Tendency - reciprocation sometimes results in unequal exchange of value.  Offering a “free” weekend for time-shares to sign up
Influence-from-Mere-Association Tendency - Two ways, actor selling X advice, other way “shoot the messenger”
Simple, Pain-Avoiding Psychological Denial - Happens in projects a lot (interest in misleading). Easy to tell stories in retrospect.  Sometimes fewer facts are more believable. Math built on faulty assumptions.
Excessive Self-regard Tendency - Genuine expert is to know your limits. Story == Confidence != Truth
Over-Optimism Tendency - “One of our biases is that we can ignore the lessons of experience.” - Kahneman.
Deprival Super-Reaction Tendency - Loss aversion, too conservative for gains, too risky for losses. “empirical evidence suggests we feel losses about two to two-and-a-half times more than we feel gains.” Mauboussin
Social-Proof Tendency - Good ideas cause more mischief than bad ideas, push good idea to retched excess. We need to copy others since we don’t have complete information. Weigh correctness by # of people. Falling in with the crowd means it’s mathematically impossible to out-perform the market. Independent thinking is arbitrage on this.
Contrast-Misreaction Tendency - Opportunity-Cost Lens averts this. Small scale, 10k add on to 65k car. Large scale bad husband because bad parents. Never comparison buy because you saw something worse first.
Stress-Influence Tendency - Avoid it.
Availability-Misweighing Tendency - availability | recency != value. I.e. buying after a crash. Or lottery tickets.
Use-It-or-Lose-It Tendency -
Drug-Misinfluence Tendency  -
Senescence-Misinfluence Tendency - Far better to wear out from work rust out from inactivity.
Authority-Misinfluence Tendency - Risk, uncertainty of Ignorance exacerbates authority tendency. Flashy suits or degrees do to.
Twaddle Tendency - Or Prattle, Don’t confidently answer questions if I don’t know. Answers are not value, truth and correctness is. Easiest person to fool is myself.
Reason-Respecting Tendency - people will defer to reason, it’s why boiler rooms work, hustle on fake reasons penny stocks will go up
Lollapalooza Tendency - Interactions of previous tendencies create sum greater than parts. Either creates critical mass or doesn’t at all, “black swan event” confluence of causes, a happens in complex systems, 2007 financial crisis.  “Well, the open-outcry auction is just made to turn the brain into mush: you’ve got social proof, the other guy is bidding, you get reciprocation tendency, you get deprival super-reaction syndrome, and the thing is going away. … I mean, it just absolutely is designed to manipulate people into idiotic behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-right-stuff&quot;&gt;The Right Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to mimick exactly what someone else does.  You can improve your ability to read, think, learn, avoid mistakes, and pay attention to the personal attributes that drive success.  The focus on learning is key.  No one is perfect, focus on continual improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient
Success comes from patience and then aggressively moving when it makes sense.
Level of activity is not correlated with value.
Focus on discovery, not prediction, can’t ever know the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disciplined
Following crowd is the easiest approach, being contrarian is a benefit. No bonus for activity in investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calm but courageous and decisive
Market returns will always be lumpy, to profit from courage you have to have cash on hand. Don’t fall into the “urge of missing out”.  Move aggressively when opportunity arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasonable Intelligent but not mislead by high IQs
Passionate interest in what is happening. High IQ can lead to overconfidence, proxy fort thinking you know things you don’t.  Know your circle of competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honest
“How nice it is to have a tyrant’s strength and how wrong it is to use it like a tyrant.” What kind of things would you not do, even if it was legal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confident and non-ideological
Aware of own limitations, stay away from decisions that are too hard. Heavy ideology sways decision making, forces your hand on hard decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long-term oriented
Pain today, gain tomorrow.  Compounding interest is hard to fully understand. Many things that are not directly financial will compound. Skills, relationships, and other aspects of life can compound and benefit a person who invests time and money wisely to cultivate these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion
Passionate people tend to have an informational edge over others who are not as passionate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studious
Read a lot. Best approach to investing is to be businesslike.  Talk to users of the business, suppliers, ex-employees, everybody (user research on the company!) Life is a lot more pleasant when you let other people make most of the big mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collegial
Surround yourself with people you can learn from - have someone trusted to talk to. Everyone needs somebody to talk to, helps refine your thoughts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound Temperament
Avoid emotional (fear, greed). Keep a record of investment decisions to review. If you don’t have this, you may not be a value investor, that’s fine, better to learn than to be an active investor with the wrong temperament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frugal
Way to wealth, waste neither time nor money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk Adverse
Volatility is just one risk and you can weigh how important it is - primary a risk for money managers as people flee funds. Risk of permanent loss, or Risk of inadequate returns are others.  Risk can’t be fully expressed as a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seven-variables-in-the-graham-value-investing-system&quot;&gt;Seven Variables in the Graham Value Investing System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 1: intrinsic value of business, is a range. too hard to value, Munger passes, should be able to do it in his head. Berkshire looks at value as it relates to ‘owners earnings’, if growth costs too much, it ‘hurts’ the investor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 2: Margin of safety, value investor have ridiculously large one where errors in calculation don’t really matter. Quality isn’t worth infinite price (FB, Nike, etc), Elevated popular opinion can be risky. Just because an expensive stock is now cheap, doesn’t necessarily create a margin of safety. No investment is so good, irrespective of price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 3: Scope of circle of competence.  circle of competence approach is a form of opportunity cost analysis, it’s not a competency if you don’t know the edge of it. Emotional intelligence fights against urge to be ‘sold’ to by good stories. Don’t conflate familiarity with competence, just because you use a product doesn’t mean you know the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 4: How much of each security to buy. Hard to go deep in many businesses, for active investors, company diversification means you likely can’t know more than the market. Goal for value investor is not to just find a quality company but a mis-priced bet. Diversification is a hedge against not knowing, low-fee index funds is the most diversified approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 5: When to sell a security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 6: how much to bet on mis priced asset.  Big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variable 7: quality of business. Important, find ones that are good, either command purchase control&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8: what businesses. Durable most,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;right-stuff-in-business&quot;&gt;Right Stuff in Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Capital allocation skills. Institutional imperative - funds soak up, resist change, justify existence, peers will follow.
2 compensation systems.
3 moat widening skills - moats win over managers, over anything.
Skin in the game.
“And in a bureaucracy, you think the work is done when it goes out of your in-basket into somebody else’s in-basket. But, of course, it isn’t.”
4 integrity in management is utmost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkshire Math
Intelligent people make decisions based on opportunity costs—in other words, it’s your alternatives that matter. That’s how we make all of our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply-Side Economies of Scale and Scope. economies of scope, a business must share resources across markets while keeping the amount of those resources largely fixed. Businesses that desire to benefit from economies of scope must avoid running as isolated units.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demand-Side Economies of Scale (Network Effects). result when a product or service becomes more valuable as more people use it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand. Brands, of course, can fail over time. determining the strength of a brand-based moat is whether a competitor can replicate or weaken the moat with a massive checkbook. Usually only the company can mess up a brand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulation. Regulations can often end up protecting existing entrenched producers rather than helping consumers. For example, some people believe banks have created such a powerful layer of regulatory expertise that the regulators have become captured by the industry they regulate. Similarly, there are a number of professional guilds, like lawyers, that have been able to use regulation to limit supply.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patents and Intellectual Property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkshires moats. Tax efficient, doesn’t pay yearly taxes on profit. Low overhead, trust managers, skin in the game. Permanent capital. Win during down cycles. Float on insurance. High quality share holders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;capitalism works is because moats are hard to create and usually deteriorate over time. What happens over time is that so-called producer surplus is transferred into consumer surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Companies generating high economic returns will attract competitors willing to take a lesser, albeit still attractive, return which will drive down aggregate industry returns to the opportunity cost of capital. —MICHAEL MAUBOUSSIN, “MEASURING THE MOAT,” 2002”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;company that has a return on capital significantly greater than its opportunity cost over time has a moat, whether they know it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture capitalists harvest something called optionality,Moats that emerge from complex adaptive systems like an economy are hard to spot. This is because a moat is something that is greater than the sum of its parts,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;factor--value-investing&quot;&gt;Factor / Value Investing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;value as a statistical factor (Fama/ French) and value as an analytical style or goal (Ben Graham). “Factor” is based on the premise that markets are efficient and use a top down approaches such as “book-to-market” used as a proxy metric for intrinsic value, another way of index investing. Grahams are bottom up based on the business, using return on equity (return / total equity) and return on capital (return / equity + debts).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Munger/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Munger/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  mastery of love</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;mastery-of-love&quot;&gt;Mastery of Love&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all masters, we all create personalities, create an image for others.  Whatever we believe comes true.  Anger - pushing problems away.  Action / Reaction.  Emotional body is full of wounds.  We live in continued fear of being hurt.  We create a big denial system.  Push buttons = pushing on wounds.  Education is just the domestication of humans, fear of not getting a reward.  We learn to pretend who we are not.  Image at home, image at school.  Man creates an image of the woman and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning we’re tuned to explore, emotional system has an alarm system of fear.   We learn to be emotional based on environment. Sense of injustice i.e. If parents unfairly hurt you.  Before these you were completely healthy.  Loose innocence, slowly goes away.  We release emotional poison on other people.  We are always judging everyone, ourselves, I’m not good enough, etc.  We will never be perfect, never good enough, always something a judge will reject.  Only punishment only suffering.  No one in the whole world will abuse you more than yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t be responsibility for someone else’s happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you will hardly remember 5% of your whole life.  You really don’t know your mother, your mother doesn’t really know you.  We have to respect everyone’s dreams.  Every relationship is a living dream.  Track of love and Track of fear.  Love has no obligations, Fear is all obligations.  Love  is based on respect, fear is not.  Self pity comes from dis-respect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Mastery-of-Love/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Mastery-of-Love/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Book  competing against luck</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;competing-against-luck&quot;&gt;Competing against luck&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data helps with product correlation, doesn’t tell you why the customers make the purchase decisions they do.  Need thesis and look for help wanted to generate causality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some product innovation frameworks are masters of description but failures of prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption theory help us investigate why some markets or companies fail - simple systems did complex ones, cheaper what it was more expensive: looking backwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jobs may exist in multiple categories, margarine and “wetting the bread : mayo”, vs “cooking : teflon”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jobs are not needs descriptions and take work to understand what people want to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress not product: understanding underlying causation on consumer decision making.  Louis Pasteur (germ theory and the causal mechanisms), need to create hypothesises and then test or look at data to prove or disprove. Much like Learn Product Development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needs (too general, i.e. “I need to eat”) and guiding principles (I want to be a good dad) are parts of the Job framework but not enough in themselves. Jobs solve obstacles that get in the way of progress towards ones goals in life. Jobs insights are stories, why they did something, not what.  What progress do they want to make (functional, social, or emotional), What are the circumstances (who, what, where, why, when), what obstacles, what compensating behaviors (imperfect solutions), what is the quality bar. Jobs can be things people want to or don’t want to do. For example, Facebook is probably competing against cigarettes, and Netflix is competing against sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circumstances matter, have to be open to find things that the theory can’t explain, this strengthens it.  Jobs theory doesn’t work out if there is no struggle or existing solutions are good enough. This is likely why “kill email” startups usually fail. Efficiency and cost are not jobs in themselves, for example High Frequency Trading is not a solution to a job. Should efficiency and costs can be part of progress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t understand jobs we end up with one-size-fits all solutions, the “One size fits none” problem. If we don’t specialize jobs we all end up building similar things. Non-consumers may hire nothing instead of something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes compensating behaviors with a job are lurking beneath the surface, enshrouded within an idea for a new product or service. These ideas bubble in from salespeople, spouses, engineers, customers and competitors. The executives who must select which ideas merit full development typically reject them because their disguise seems uninspiring. Often, however, the solution needs to be peeled away to reveal the unarticulated job that the inventor had seen needing a better solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A core reason why marketers in most companies say one thing (that they know markets ought to be segmented by job) and yet do another (they segment by product and customer category) is rooted in the easy availability of the latter sort of data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you find jobs?&lt;/em&gt; Barriers to progress or frustrating experiences: innovation opportunity. Identifying unusual workarounds: enabling something new.  Look at timeline of use, progress or frustration may happen earlier in the steps to solve, or when the purchase decision is made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jobs theory is an integration tool, integrates various theories of user profiles, an almagamation of needs, it break downs complexity, tells the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;”Perspective is worth 80 IQ points”&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t need to throw away the current data (personalities, markets, etc).  Think about creating a “mini-documentary”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Job hunting strategy&lt;/em&gt; Seeing jobs in your own life. In the Walkman case, market research didn’t work, but CEO wanted it. Kahn academy, other courses weren’t fun, other things were stressful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opportunity in non consumption.&lt;/em&gt; Competing with nothing, where is unseen demand, many times existing data doesn’t show this.  AirBnb for example, 60% of guests wouldn’t have traveled at all, largest hotelier without any real estate. The Depends adult diapers marketing push: “Reclaim your life”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Identifying workaround / compensating behaviors.&lt;/em&gt; People creating their own solutions because something is so difficult. ING Direct, took away lots of blockades, job was to get a simple bank account for unserved market. Square did this with credit card payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What we don’t want to do.&lt;/em&gt; Sick child, whole afternoon is shot taking them to the DR.  CSV came up with the minute clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unusual usages of products.&lt;/em&gt; Baking soda, laundry detergent, etc.  “Clean and Fresh everywhere”.  People were using it in so many different ways.  Z-Quil, reformulation of NyQuil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to look all around the job before you can solve, not just functional, but social and emotional.  “Crinkly paper in the dr office”, paper is designed for function, but not emotional.  “Design for people”. UX is not just a pretty screen - have to get out in the wild to live it.  “Pampers diapers in china”. Functional is great, it let’s baby sleep through the night, key insight was allow Mom and Dad to be intimate, “best 10c I ever spent said dad”: this is the emotional / social aspect of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better to message “this product is not for you”, than have a customer hire our product for the wrong reasons, they’ll come back and blame you. This is a great insight, that way you don’t try to build features for people that the product doesn’t really fit for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at non-consumers vs. just the people using your or similar products.  Pay close attention to compensating behaviors or unusual uses of the current products. What consumer hire and fire tells a great story. Consumers can’t always articulate what they want.  Most people say they want to be good to environment, but what is on your shelfs?  Disposable diapers?  “Organic” People hire products and make trade offs in those particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important Questions:&lt;/em&gt;
What are the important unfulfilled jobs in your own lives
What jobs do you use them to get done?
Who is not consuming your products today?  Where do they fall short? What is stopping them?&lt;br /&gt;
What circumstances do they use the products?  What does this reveal about the nature?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Hire vs Little Hire.&lt;/em&gt; Big is the purchase, little is the time and time again usage, i.e. App downloads vs # times it’s opened.  &lt;strong&gt;What has to get fired for my product to get hired?&lt;/strong&gt;  Forces compelling changes in a certain circumstances, if it’s just nagging or annoying it might not be enough to cause someone to switch, it has to be an obstacle them from making progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two forces opposing change.&lt;/em&gt; Habits of the present.  Anxiety of something new.  “Devil you know” and “loss aversion” is twice as powerful as any gains promised. In the ING case, not having a real location made people feel unsafe. ING Direct cafe makes it feel like a real bank, even though you can’t do anything there.  The new has to be great than the sum of inertia of the old and and the anxieties of the new.  Functional is easier to fire, emotional / social is harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full picture of progress, competing needs, what they need to fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to map this out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are they trying accomplish (struggles).  Storyboarding, sketch it out.  What is their desire for something new.  The more realistic it is, emotional.  The first little hire moment.  The story must match the vision for what they want to hire.  The moments of struggle, tradeoff, customers seek progress but are inhibited.  Cluster together stories to see if there are any similarities.  Have a beginners mind, complete picture of the struggle.  Timeline of all the triggers that led to the decision.  The impulse picture that wasn’t - purchases never just happen.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Competing-against-luck/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/books/2017/11/25/Book-Competing-against-luck/</guid>


        <category>books</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>5 Ideas</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some more dumb ideas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play audio playlist tool that you could share your best childhood songs with your child at the relevant ages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auto remixer for the ADD economy, it would put together clips of music, and soundbites from CNN or podcasts that were interesting and play that in a 30 minute loop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Headphones shaped like your ear but just looked a little bit bigger so that it looked like you had a giant ears.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote concerts that are streamed to live to your living room, and the visual/light show projected behind or around the band is controlled by a consensus algorithm between phone apps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free live stream concerts that are advertised on alcohol containers that you bring home like wine or beer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/ideas/2017/10/12/5-ideas/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/ideas/2017/10/12/5-ideas/</guid>


        <category>ideas</category>

      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Tedx Sf Notes And Thoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;2017-tedx&quot;&gt;2017 TedX&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother-in-law and wife gave me a great gift, tickets to this years TEDx SF. What follows are some notes and thoughts on the conference. The opportunity to step outside of the day-to-day tech mind space and explore various topics with thought leaders was enthralling. The frontier of what is possible due to ever cheaper technology, scalable distributed learning, and the passion for making a better side in the future is truly inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quentin Hardy&lt;/strong&gt;
Fear and compassion drives social progress?  Where is the fear today about what is next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;precision&quot;&gt;Precision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atul Butte&lt;/strong&gt;
Quantified Self: Learning is precise, doesn’t matter if data roughly inaccurate. Feedback cycles between devices collecting and analysis / interpretation, does this have to be a human? Probably. De-identification.  Data visualization of people moving between sickness states, then identify percentage of likely hold.
&lt;em&gt;Idea&lt;/em&gt;: ResistBot style ‘get my medical records’ and forward to another service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrew Hessel&lt;/strong&gt;
We can program cells today (Autodesk is doing this?) Synthetic yeast project.   Human Genome 2?  Mainly focused around synthetic biology, scientists weren’t sharing. GP-write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neil Grimmer&lt;/strong&gt;
Can you personalize food?  Habit company personalizing food?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew Sweeney&lt;/strong&gt;
Smart to start with medicine delivery, clear need, urgent and tool to break through regulation.  Cardiac arrest, deliver defibrillators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sebastian De Halleux&lt;/strong&gt;
Ocean data is scarce, but what are we trying to measure, could it predict hurricanes? Neat approach to solar sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;currencies&quot;&gt;Currencies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rebecca Altman&lt;/strong&gt;
Plastics usage lifespan, refrigerators to lids for coffee cups. Polystyrene being eaten by plankton and eventually ending up inside us.  8.3B metric tons of plastic.  In 4 generations plastics have changed significantly - why are we so locked into disposable plastics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew Roszak&lt;/strong&gt;
Golem? Civic? Every tribe can tokenize their economy, award points, incentivize early adopters.  SpaceChain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arthur Breitman&lt;/strong&gt;
Keynesian game - shilling point - if communication is expensive, they will find a solution.  Like all currencies people have to accept it, abide by the rules, based on the shilling point.  Lots of active research, why? # of Arxiv papers.  How do you move the shilling point? Forks are one approach.  Play for legitimacy, using authority to creating that (Satoshi says).  Forks are like a game of chicken, not an effective way to do governance.  Focus on the common parts, we all have to innovate, how? Has to be merit focused, otherwise you get shilling points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mar Cabra&lt;/strong&gt;
CableGate, PanamaPaper, Record numbers of leaks and document dumps. Sharing is not the natural step for journalists.  Federation is the only way to deal with the amount of data that is produced.  Since everything is logged, this just gets harder.  Pulitzer’s prize for Panama Paper, all made possible but the ICIJ.  How do we archive and verify?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabe Zichermann&lt;/strong&gt;
832m people are alcoholics? Everyone is an addict, the dopamergic loop makes us survive and push our lineage forward.  Addiction treatments are really poor, need to think about it like preventative treatment, how to vaccinate people? Onward does this with Chatbot, AI.  Own AI to block other gamified attempts to hi-jack your behavior or consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;empathy&quot;&gt;Empathy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jane Metcalf&lt;/strong&gt;
Partnership of Biome, Josiah the Oden crispr at home hacker, crazy ethical complications. Biohacker and citizen scientists exploring solutions, NIST is interested.  We can be afraid or curious.  Video games for ADHD?  Synthetic Biology. Mango Materials, was methane to textiles.  Already changing humans, selecting out mental health traits. “Unnatural selection”, germ-line editing.  So much mis information in food, social echo tribal chamber.  “NoGMO” on Salt, so ridiculous, FUD.   Date to change your mind. What kind of species are we designing?  Neo.life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joon Yun&lt;/strong&gt;
Homeostatic capacity goes away over life, need to change what we measure.  Heart rate doesn’t change, but response to exercise - need some temporal resolution on diagnostics.  Capacity building, try to prop stuff up (like blood pressure medicine).  Make the body stronger what about giving blood pressure increasing medicine instead of lowering.  Interesting thought about gene evolution works in death, but for knowledge.  Stretch your range, we’re only species that goes towards the medium.  Exercise different times of the day, different things.  Meditate and Exhilarate. Increase dynamic range.  Happy and Sad.  Improve on Stage.  Functional Longevity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elaine Fong&lt;/strong&gt;
What do you do when you are asked to design death?  Death with Dignity in Washington, but Dr said “no” to sign off it.  Easy to think of design as asthetics.  But it’s a means of communication.  DwD requires design because it requires discussion, a shared language, with a common goal.  How difficult does a system need to be to say you want to die.  Death is a universal experience, conversation we all have to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Adkins&lt;/strong&gt;
Pinksocks gifting is cool, neat to see burning man ideas percolating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fran Guijaro&lt;/strong&gt;
What other words are like the SF fog, hiding stories.  Homelessness is one, what are others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jack Gallant&lt;/strong&gt;
1/3 of brains are the same in functional areas, 2/3’s are not.  FMRI is spatial, EEG is temporal.  Will be there soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dan Everett&lt;/strong&gt;
Language is the first and best technology, homo erectus was around for 2m years 1/4 of sapiens. They explored. Even with only 11 sounds, they could communicate with only 2 (1,0 analogy).  3 signs.  Indexes to physical world, Icon physical resemblance, Symbol culturally determined.  G1, G2, G3 grammars.  G1 is ordered word “drink, drive, jail”, G2 is hierarchical, G3 hierarchy and recursion. All animals communicate, but only humans use language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Socher&lt;/strong&gt;
Athelas.com counting blood cells, sentiment analysis, 2-iter DNM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intelligence&quot;&gt;Intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Omoju Miller&lt;/strong&gt;
Knowledge is acquired not infused, like you extend a building.  Knowledge to come into your life, logical form and emotional form. Myth of innate ability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemave.com/blog/2017/10/10/tedx-sf-notes-and-thoughts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemave.com/blog/2017/10/10/tedx-sf-notes-and-thoughts/</guid>


        <category>blog</category>

      </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
