<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>An avenue of ways</title>
    <description>Musings on life, technology and audio.
</description>
    <link>http://willemsavenue.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://willemsavenue.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 21:36:43 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 21:36:43 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Algorithms to live by</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Optimal stopping problem. Aka the secretary problem. 
Time to a search if unbounded. If number of candidates is fixed. If no incomplete information, observation only, then 37% is optimal. If full information, score and only that score matters. Never hire unless it’s the best you’ve seen so far, 58%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selling a house, know objective dollar value, and rough range. Not single best, most money, waiting has a cost. Set one going in, take first option to exceed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore vs Exploit.
Always exploring can be frustrating. Multi-armed bandit problem and casino’s.  Time is the key value, exploring goes down over time, exploit goes up. Need to discount payoffs based on time. You care more about the meal tonight than the one a month from now, geometrically discounting. Giddens Index. If you don’t have time, think about regret. Total amount of regret will always increase, minimize regret. Regret Minimization Algorithms. Upper Confidence Bound. Choose the one with the highest confidence bound, it’s always greater than the expected value. Optimism fights against regret. High value of the 0/0 (try/win) option. Win-stay, loose-shift explores too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorting.
Sometimes sorting isn’t worth the time, only if your searching. Fault tolerant sorting, were comparisons have error bars, you want more comparisons like bubble or counting sort. In animal pecking order, sorting helps against larger amounts of antagonizing. Cardinal ordering like races allow for O(n) to sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caching.
LRU is most efficient,along many axes such as geography. 
Ebbinghouse forgetfulness curve, Brain has unlimited storage, limiting factor for is time. This is also how society organizes information. 
More memory is slower, interesting collelary with age. Maybe older people are slower because they have to search though more stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scheduling.
Inputs/goals are usually due date, number of workers, throughout or latency. Look from outsiders perspective, sun of completion time, or shortest thing first, can also weight these and divide duration by weight. Procrastination is like DDOS, doing lots of small things of low weight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 09:10:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2019/01/15/Algorithms-to-live-by/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2019/01/15/Algorithms-to-live-by/</guid>
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>5 years</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Five years, many things can happen in five years. Five years ago I was diagnosed with Stage IIIa testicular cancer. So I’m writing this post on the milestone that my cancer is officially in remission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m dedicating this post to my wonderful wife, KJ, who creates the best for everyone in her life. I’m eternally grateful to have had you with me on this journey. Otherwise, I’m not sure I would have made it in one piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife, who was my girlfriend at the time, is one to make sure something gets done. I had an ache in my groin area and hadn’t thought much about it. We had done a pretty long bike ride a couple weeks before. This is a case where internet diagnoses didn’t help, I had I read an article that bike riding and groin injuries are common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t go away and a few days later KJ bugged me enough and I finally went to get it checked out. After a brief diagnoses, the doctor was alarmed and mentioned that he had a urologist friend a few floors down, and I should go see him immediately. The urologist, who, I kid you not, was called Dr. Duong, was about to leave to go home but made some time to check me out. After a quick check, Dr. Duong sent me to get an ultrasound.  Luckily there was a Sutter Health right across the street, and we got an ultrasound scheduled for later that evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the next few hours were the proverbial hurricane. The ultrasound came back as positive for bi-lateral tumors. On my way to getting my blood drawn, I called my girlfriend. Now  this is where memory is such a funny thing, I don’t recall exactly what we talked about, but needless to say, emotions were running high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-first-weekend&quot;&gt;The first weekend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Duong wanted to operate quickly. Testicular cancer is very fast moving and can travel up the lymphatic pathways to the brain in short order. We didn’t want to jump right into surgery as KJ and I had a lot of questions. Feeling completely out of our league, it was time to fall into the help of my family and friends. I cannot thank KJ, our parents and Evan’s family friend who was also urologist for their guidance. The operation had many implications to our future together, it was impossible comprehend he full extent. Kids? Not from my genetic material. Testosterone therapy? Yup, for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my death pebbles were out, the final diagnoses came in. The cancer had metastasized, and I would need to go through chemo. I got a referral to an oncologist and we started setting up a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tahoe&quot;&gt;Tahoe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a yearly family trip to Tahoe with KJ’s family scheduled. After my surgery, I hadn’t seen my parents yet, so we invited them up to Tahoe and away we went. How was I feeling? Purgatory probably describes it well, knowing that the tumor was out, but that the cancer matastizised. The holding pattern before chemo is used to let your body strengthen so it could handle the chemical load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since chemo causes your hair to fall out, we figured it to shorten it up. For the longest time I always had a standard side-parted hair cut, now that was all going to change. Now, some for a little glimpse into why hair was important to me. Every male adult in my in the ancestor tree has been bald. As a kid I was frightened at the prospect of being bald in my 20’s as my dad had been. But ce la vie, a few glasses of wine in and the clippers came out. My mom had the honors of buzzing my hair and while the $20 CVS clippers almost died along the way, we triumphed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chemo&quot;&gt;Chemo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testicular cancer is usually treated with the BEP protocol. While it’s about 3 months in duration, relatively short compared to others, but it makes up for it in intensity. It roughly breaks down to one week of 8a-5p chemo infusion and then one week off for your body to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BEP protocol is bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin. Wow that’s a mouthful. The whole goal of chemo is to stop “fast growth cells” like tumors, and coincidentally hair, nails and white blood cells. You may wonder how it works, it’s actually pretty fascinating. The main action is to unwind your RNA to an extent that cell replication breaks. Then, start attacking the tumor with a heavy metal (platinum) which kills it. Slow replicating cells like red and white blood cells keep working, but fast replicating cells just die off. So this is the chemo dance. Kill parts of your body in measured ways so that the medicine can elimate the cancerous cells, before you kill all the good things that are in your body!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day you get your blood taken, if your white or red blood cells are too low, then that means the balance is off and you delay treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s it actually like? Well, these days they load you up with great anti-nauseous medicine and steroids so it’s bareable. I’d liken it to a 3 month hang overs, except without any of the fun drinking parts. Food does start to taste crappy and you loose about 40 pounds. The weirdest part is one day you’ll be in the shower and your hair will start to fall out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;ChemoTreatment.png&quot; alt=&quot;Treatment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bookfresh&quot;&gt;BookFresh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about work? So here’s where the story gets interesting. I was CTO of a company, BookFresh. It was an exciting time for BF, we were growing at close to 8% MoM and the team was executing well. On the off week for chemo, I tried to goto work, usually it was fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some partnership interest from a company called Square. At one point during chemo, we had to give a product demo. I vividly remember that it was a few days after I had noticed my hair starting to fall out in the shower. I remember thinking, well I hope it doesn’t look too weird for our meeting! I made a small mental note not to rub my head during the demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 Month after my chemo finished we were acquired by Square and my Square journey began (I’m still there!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friends-and-family&quot;&gt;Friends and Family&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how did I make it through? KJ made the world wonderful. Everything from working with doctors, going with me to every appointment, to getting me treats during the long days of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amazing support from all my friends was truly heartbreaking. I’m fortunate to have some of the best, kindest friends in the world. During the treatment I got a table full of cards and clever gifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After chemo, KJ organized the most heartwarming moment, one I’ll remember forever. She planned a get together with all my friends from all over the world to come to SF. We celebrated in our true fashion with a trek to the Treasure Island Music Festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading, onward!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/blog/life/2019/01/10/5-years/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/blog/life/2019/01/10/5-years/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mastering the Market Cycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is unknowable future, for gains and losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An edge is an information edge, tendencies (likely to happen) need to take into account factors. Hard to know how far back, impossible to define when “cycle starts or ends” but can look at peak to peak or trough to trough. Regression to the mean. Mean generally has a secular trend upward. Events can build on each other like stored energy, do not happen in isolation. Largely driven by psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returns are better when investors are fearful and worse when greedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different types of cycles that can interact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One time events Are difficult to identify the tendency, given lots of exgenerous factors, I.e. earnings calls&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long term cycles: Since GDP = hours worked * productivity. GDP therefore is largely impacted by birth rates. Drive to work (vs communism), automation (vs loss of people working and consumption). Averge generally goes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short term cycles: psychology, yearly GDP doesn’t really matter. wealth effect, people feel good spend more. Unconventional Forecasts are rarely right and can’t be used generally, mainly gambling. Hindsight bias priases these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endogenous: hiring more
exogenous: war, tax changes, pricing cartels, droughts,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government’s cycles: central Banks, Hawks make changes fast and perhaps too far. Doves help growth with stimulation packages. Deficits that help drive demand can be useful for growth. CBs try to drive counter cyclical, very hard to get right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profits cycles: larger effect on some companies rather than others. Food and Staples are more consistent, industrial equipment is closer. Very dependent on type business. Sales growth (GDP) does not = GDP due to costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed income = known loss because equity holder loose before debt holders, a fixed outcome. If company is pure equity, any loss or change in operating behavior flows directly to bottom line (net income). Debt is leverage and shows up more on net income incases of changes to operating costs, financial leverage at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology cycles affect operating profits by doing things more efficiently and increasing competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors psychology cause excess swings. Greed, fear pendulum. There are others. Euphoria &amp;gt; Optimism and depression. This also effects between skepticism and potential. Affects how people came the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Superior investor, few people are even keeled. Looking at intrinsic value + future value.
Emotional driven actions follow either: Selective perception and skewed interpretation. Not the data or events rather how people interpret them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events aren’t predicable and hence risk, primary challenge. We can only deal with environment as it is. Risk is not linear wrt return, appear to have higher return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk aversion changes based on environment. Change premiums, lose interest in the lower end of the spectrum. Changes the capital markets line, the slope of line is how risk averse is the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit spreads, government 5 to corporate 6, as trust flows that way, same with maturity, hence credit spreads and yield curves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk tolerance avoids reasonable thought, risky behavior on financial events. Race to bottom for larger finance firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Story about yields on bonds during financial crisis, and consecutive negative questions about “how bad can it get”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much optimism is baked into the price? How much skepticism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look for optimism when pesissim runs amok. Investors typically oscillate between there is not a risk in sight, and I don’t wanna lose another dollar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit cycle. Like A window, which can shut in an incident. GDP the only TV but if you percentage points from the trend line, profits only deviate by a few percentage points from the trendlines. Financial leverage causes reported profits to swing or widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit cycles can affect even short term borrowing towards long-term assets because people typically roll over these deaths and need new capital to continue funding. If you don’t have cash on hand to pay this becomes a problem in this affects financial institutions more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lend it, they will build it, sometimes recklessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is just like any other commodity, when is cheap people lend with loose terms, this is the race to the bottom. This is how lending firms “compete” by offering successively worse deals, as credit is plentiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GFC, low interest rates and race to bottom for “money commodity”. Credit window closes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closed windows. Investors are depressed. Hard to refinance, etc. Because of fear, makes most people afraid to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open windoes, cheap deals, buyers raise money, unwise extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t come only from high quality assets, but when deals are good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distressed debt cycle:
Chain reaction from easy credit to lower credit worthy was high yield debts, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Stacks logs on the bonfire”. Needs an ignitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning words: “ever increasing”, “this time is different”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors job, bull makers top and bear markets  bottom are by definition related to psychology or immature investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If only earnings prices wouldn’t fluctuate much more than prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distorted views, quirks like confirmation bias, non linear utility, tall tales, risk tolerance and version, herd behavior, extreme discomfort was watching other people make money, give up on valuable investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prices are fundamentals (events like earnings and cash flow) and psychology (how we respond to fundamentals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a cycle in the wave of psychology that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the wisemen does in the beginning, the fool does at the end. innovator, imitators, idiot. Very hard to watch your friends make money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mania to always talk about bubble. Not every big rise is a bubble. Hallmark is “no price too high” use leverage to keep making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in cycle is a potential for a return, lower potential earlier, higher later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for: Economy: Vibrant Sluggish Outlook: Positive Negative Lenders: Eager Reticent Capital markets: Loose Tight Capital: Plentiful Scarce Terms: Easy Restrictive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What some people wish for, they end up believing” - demoicles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no silver bullet, otherwise person selling would hoard or prices would go up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most bubbles happen because of Unquestioning acceptance of things that haven’t been true in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial reflexivity: Thinking participants can affect markets because of their distorted views. Similar to wishes affecting beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impossible to know when the bottom is, focus on fundamentals, historical price value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to do this, try to travel into the future and back test assumptions. No tactics that always work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycle positioning. Agressiveness: timing: skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Cycle positioning, asset selection
2) agressiveness and defensiveness
3) reasonable assumption, generally correct,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negative skill - when flipping a coin is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/11/02/Mastering-the-Market-Cycle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/11/02/Mastering-the-Market-Cycle/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Superforecasting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Forecasters are just Chips throwing darts at a dartboard, little better than guessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butterfly effect, LaPlasses Deamon, lorenzes cloud. We live in a world of predictability and unpredictability. Prediction accuracy for Forecasts That have a component of chaotic for butterfly affect, will converge towards 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;forecasts are used for everything from Banks promising financial gain, to pundits saying they know the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System one and system two in the cognitive reflection test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We impose order on the world, why we can make System 1 decisions sounds d sane even when there is better evidence. Split brain test, Different hemispheres of the brain are shown different pictures, but the brain creates a story about both of them. sometimes the best positive test is the test where you prove the negative and it turns out to be false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any forecasting should clarify different nouns and verbs in the statement. Like The word possible which ranges from 0 to 100%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging judgment. Must have many forecasts to look at judgment. Resolution and calibration. Resolution is how far away from 50/50, calibration is percent of time correct. Briar score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big idea forcasters fit everything into that model, doggedly try to fit relativity into their view, worse than dart throwing chimps. Emerald City and green glasses. May increase confidence but not accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collective judgment is generally more accurate. Useful information is usually spread out. Min / max cancel each other out. Individual Forecasts may be better. Good forcasters do internal aggregation. Think about other people, rational Vulcan, pseudo radical, aggregators, gut guessers. IE the guess the numbers game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasonable vs correct&lt;/strong&gt;, don’t look at outcomes, look at the way it was analyzed. Can be reasonable and wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test everything, doubt everything, red teams, AB tests, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisdom of crowd is just aggregation of information, once you have this, can increase confidence once you have this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Randomness can for you, one person Getting 100 coin tosses 70% correct is extremely unlikely, but 2000 people guessing will be close. Similar to the fallacy of guessing the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regression to the mean is a powerful concept. in completely random coin toss, if very lucky people got 90% ones they would have more likely hit 10% next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fermi-estimates, Breaking down the question into it’s constituents parts. identifying the knowable from the unknowable. Fermi-zing, and confidence intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside view vs. outside view. inside view is data you look at within the event. Outside view is trend or historical data for data related to that event. Better to start with outside to ensure eyou anchor with out being involved in the.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fermi-ize&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outside view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inside view based on fermi-ize questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesize both&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be Actively open minded, seek other opinions, weight them equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid the in, Wide variance and probability can lead people to go into a ignorance Pryor. there is a primal instincts to align with certainty, even though it is against our best System two judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ailiatory uncertainty (like prericiti g the weather) will always exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porbabilistic thinkers focus on the how it happened vs the why. Be wary of substituting my sorry of beliefs for the one I’m analyzing. IE if person x is likely to make a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under or over updating: Achilles heel of forcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t need full Bayes equations. Just update priors based on the weight of new evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink: we cannot all be wrong, don’t mistake agreement for correctness. Ask precision questions, don’t question the person or ask vague “what do you mean” unless the person is being ambiguous. Criticism is helpful, I want to hear feedback. Don’t Dance and the issues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to invite criticism more?&lt;/strong&gt;
Givers, matchers, takers, flow of information and questions are critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrarian thinking can help inject new information into the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nothing like Danger to focus the mind” -soros&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distinguish what you are confident about and what you’re not. Look part the end of your nose. Self doubt is not the answer, intellectual humility is key, careful reflection, confidence can inspire determinate action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t mistake facts from values, especially when looking at actions by others or organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahneman: 
scope insensitivity, you imagine the one for the many when valuing something. Need a multiplier. &lt;strong&gt;Scope can include time as well!&lt;/strong&gt;
WYSIWTI - What you see is what there is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black swan investing == VC
Forecast investing 60% more modest gains.
Perhaps possible to forcasters could sequences of black swan events.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/10/18/Superforecasting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/10/18/Superforecasting/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deep work</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Shifts into easier more logistic work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network tools move things from deep to shallow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Average is over, technology segments and remote work will raise up stars and also allow for deeper thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas pickety notes that it is difficult to quantify the work of an individual as an organization grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurring meetings and lots of emails force people in to the path of least resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/10/15/Deep-work/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/10/15/Deep-work/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Oxford Guide to effective argument</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thinking critically is judging strength or weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions vs noun phrases, generally stating association between two objects. Look out for the explicitness of a claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons give grounds for accepting the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an argument when P and Q have an inference from one another. (P, and so Q). the most basic argument is an inference from a claim (P → Q). Explanation does not equate to argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SLOW FOG - is conclusion, reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyze claims to see which are reasons and which are conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;titles-as-questions&quot;&gt;titles as questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title -&amp;gt; statement -&amp;gt; reason -&amp;gt; conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good idea to break questions down into sub-questions - great ways to stress thinking, break out assumptions. Set parts of your argument into meaningful order, give direction. Reasons and Conclusion should we weighted equally. Don’t infer more than the reasons imply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-you-make-yourself-clear&quot;&gt;How will you make yourself clear?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title.
Determine scope of your argument. Ie focus, time span, geography, etc. Smaller target is easier to hit.
Be careful of words with multiple meanings.
In an argument, make assumptions clear.
Statement = where you stand.
Ambiguity = multiple meanings.
Slippery use of words is self defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordering / Indicating: 
Claim (P) -&amp;gt; Explanation (E) -&amp;gt; Inference (Q)
Order for reasons can go from small to big, specific to general, early to late, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;avoid vagueness by defining the key terms that you will use; ￼ be precise about the scope of your argument; ￼ be aware of any assumptions that you may be making; ￼ take care not to use ambiguous language; ￼ be wary of conflating terms that ordinarily have different uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-case-have-other-made&quot;&gt;what case have other made?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counter claim. Can give readers a point of reference. Need reasons why counter is better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/09/26/Oxford-Guide-to-effective-argument/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/09/26/Oxford-Guide-to-effective-argument/</guid>
        
        <category>in_progress</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scaling Up Excellence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Scaling up Excellence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is messy
Scaling depends on people
Focus on you first&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on the ground battles not the air battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grit drives people to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spread-of-mindset-just-a-footprint&quot;&gt;Spread of mindset just a footprint.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;engage-all-the-senses&quot;&gt;Engage all the senses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It in a grocery store playing French music cause people to buy French products. if people were in a sent in a scented were more likely to keep it clean. You can boost mindset with a lot of tons of tiny queues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accelerate-accountability&quot;&gt;Accelerate accountability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tug of responsibility is felt by everyone. Transparency, Leaderboards, Showong your work, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoiding-the-clusterfuck&quot;&gt;Avoiding the clusterfuck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cluster from military, not enough skilled officers
Illusion and patience and confidence, and instill a healthy dose of doubt and worry
Sources from habits or culture must be changed as things scale. Like AllHands for everyone. 
Whittle away cognitive and emotional burdens from old world.
Addition and subtraction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slow-down-to-go-fast-system-1-vs-2&quot;&gt;Slow down to go fast, system 1 vs 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;System 1 is like old cukutres and habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bhuddism-or-catholicism&quot;&gt;bhuddism or Catholicism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top down and told why, or a mindset and let people decide.
“I like, I wish”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See’s Candies, In n Oit, Intel == Catholicism. Works well when standardization and Precision Is requireda for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch out for the replica trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way is not always better than the other, but look for over standardization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you suffer from delusions of uniqueness? Too often we fool ourselves, why are you special? Knee surgery, 5% of customization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;replication needs an example to succeed. ImPossible to pick and choose best practices as there are no examples to back them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starbucks, copies Italian, but improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will bolstering Buddhism increase commitments and understanding?
Buddhism is great to experiment, own goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dips in Excellence are temporary and predictable in the learning curve as you scale up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s better to roll and inferior solution to optimize for learning. Guard rails can help allow for local optimization. Specify the least number of guardrails necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic incentives can help align the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scaling-principles&quot;&gt;Scaling principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change Belief or Behavior? - both strategy is are mutually reenforcing. Emotions are contagious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stanford and helmets, using watermelons to show, got buy in from soccer team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JetBlue, do then speak, Drew out a process map. Large cross functional team. Guiding principle of “Cancel, Repair, communicate”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scope out scaling challenges between reinforcing beliefs and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name the problem - compact summary of the problem, helps if it’s catchy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name the enemy - If people feel threatened through a external threat, Pick a target, freeze it and polarize it. Steve Jobs, MS and Dell. Worry about embracing it too strongly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do it where all can see - Ghandi and Salt walk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breach assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create gateway experiences and on ramps - ie cleaning up a plant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New rituals, better rituals- doing some things voluntarily and publicly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lean on people who can’t leave good alone, perhaps younger
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Be a Poet and a Plumber”
Mindset is a compass&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cut-cognitive-load&quot;&gt;Cut cognitive load&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules tools and fools
Can only store 7 numbers in short term memory. Miller number. More metric, more goals do not always help. 
Multitasking hurts, scaling can help people multitask more.
Larger groups have higher cognitive load, connections are exponential, Dunbar number.
Reduce the heirarchy, heirarchy helps with communication, clear roles, clear roles.
Don’t over simplify,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shit detector, throw away what isn’t working, need to subtract as we scale. Cut cognitive load.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substraction: As scaling unfolds sometimes you need to inject complexity, then remove it. Simplistic -&amp;gt; complex -&amp;gt; profound simplicity. Liking to Exposure of stimulus grows algorimically - why subtraction is hard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subtraction via addition, load busters. Subtracting large teams and adding smaller pods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incentives, money, goals, Swapping roles can help show empathy across teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bolster collective brainpower. Team performance is not linked to initial intelligence. “Hard Teams” help with execution, and on complex or time sensitive tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rest, sleep helps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give ground grudgingly. Coordination neglect. Stay vigilant. Run things a little hot, add process when needed. Still need slack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When accountability evaporates people’s passion goes away, involves a “used to attitude”. Just talent is not having a no assholes policy helps. Talent density matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netflix treats annual performance review as a “rehire”, what would this person make if they were hired else where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accountability: I own the place, and the place owns me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free rider is a selfish problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free riser problem is asymmetric. Incentives, external and internal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inject pride and riteous anger, can drive fewer selfish desires.“Properly bed, fed and led” - army general.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Guilt prone leaders”, work hard and unselfishly. Do what is best for greater good. If people feel guilty they will do the behaviors that are best for their organization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’ll be watching you” - subtle remind that other people may be watching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create the right gene pool, company becomes people it hires. Can reengineer the pool as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find people or Companies hope you hiring, acting as a filter. Teach for America program and stanfords coordinator program&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire people pre-wired for your mindset. Autistic consulting company for testing. Taj hotel and finding people who put customers first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like working out, stressing an org can be beneficial, as it scales, stress can be of many forms. Lack of process, rotating super stars, transparency, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-using-social-bonds-to-spread-excellent&quot;&gt;Chapter 6 using social bonds to spread excellent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core team the information and guidance flowing. 
Find helpers, train then up, core team can not push over ever Domino.
Can’t just spread something good over everything. Need pockets of excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;identify people that could replace you, having a keen eye for talent is aultiploer.
&lt;em&gt;Energizer&lt;/em&gt; not necessarily bubbly.
After a conversation with someone you know more energized or less energized. This is a great way to frame if you want someone on your team not or company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;avoid “murder boards”, gamify the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually you have to use multiple methods to reinforce the message. 
Top down. Broadcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scaling up Excellence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pairing people up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brokers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transparency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideo Kelly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listener&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speak last&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change direction when new information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the rituals that matter, but the rythym&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signals things aren’t working, few lunches and smiles, or conversly, to interconnected and confidence bias&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad behavior Cascades just like others&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;its not my problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commons problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each person person Ally obligated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone agrees on what bad bevhior looks like&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure bad behavior is not normalized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad behavior:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plumbing before poetry. Weed out bad behevaior before preaching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use cool kids to squalch bad behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kill the thrill of bad behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timeshifting - show the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good Times bad Times and the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahneman: No matter how good of long something is, the best and worst experiences will drive the memory of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applies to people coming and leaving to the team as well (say lay offs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;dangerous feelings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear of standing up - silence is dangerous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear of being ostracized. Embarrassment works if aligned with pride&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anonymity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helplessness, need to say that past will not affect, focus on tactical wins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premortems:
start with outcome, work backwards, forces near and long term thinking “given this failed, what happened”. What if another company launched this same thing, what happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where to begin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scaling needs grit, way more than planning and kickoffs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design needs constrains, more imaginative solutions when guidelines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job of hierarchy is to remove the hierarchy,does it enable creativity or hamper?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t always need to be friends, hire people you respect, need to work together regardless if they are friends. Empower people to take different opinions, &lt;strong&gt;productive friction&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutual respect, Fight as you are right, listen as you are wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I own the place and the place owns me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pride&quot;&gt;Pride&lt;/h2&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/09/26/Scaling-up/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/09/26/Scaling-up/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Good strategy / bad strategy</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-strategy&quot;&gt;What is Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategy is identifying the few challenges or opportunities and alining resources towards them. Example: General Petraeus and identifying in Iraq to support the populist, turn them against the insurgents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental guide points&lt;/strong&gt;
Escalating fixed costs: Film, Kodak. IBM and integrated costs.
Deregulation: Regulated prices help subsidize one customer for another customer.many subsidized companies have trouble with new world of accounting.
Biases and forecasting: Models suffer from mean problems, growth usually follows growth. Durable goods are more variables.
Properly asses incumbent response to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy and strategic planning are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-strategy&quot;&gt;Bad Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad strategy just highlights overly broad ambitious goals, without clear language, buzzwords, ambition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fluff, Esoteric abstract statements, complexity (ie enron bandwidth markets).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doesn’t articulate the challenge, or obstacles, can be internal or external obstacles. Eg: (DARPA strategy for high risk, hi reward innovation identifies internal obstacles to innovation such as empire building and expensive office in has, strategy of rotating out project leads every 4 to 6 years)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mistaking goals for strategy. What is our leverage, taking market share is not strategy.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You still need resource planning. Strategy bridges goals with objectives. eg: freedom is goal, defeat Taliban is objective)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bad strategic objectives. Objectives should be achievable, not blue sky. Also a limited set of these. eg: of blue sky (transformational leadership).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vision is not a substitute for a strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad strategy: “we need to work with others to defuse local issues”. Good strategy: would include why those things are issues, why working with people that we currently are isn’t enough, which instruments would be used on this crusade. Bad strategy doesn’t address the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forcing Choice in actions of a strategy causes people to sharpen their arguments. Universal buy-in is the absence of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When strategy succeeds no one remembers the things you said no to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“New thought” was dangerous: As long as you believe it is possible is insane. Through the power of new thoughts and positive thinking permeated all the way into strategy. Need to make choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;good-strategy&quot;&gt;Good Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good strategy needs to identify Challenges + Diagnoses, Guiding policy, and Coherent actions (resources, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy should have actions, some people mistake strategy with goals and goal setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good strategy includes a shift in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked Jobs said that his strategy for the PC Market was too wait for the next big thing. Strategy is just as much about what we do not as what we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Walton redefine the definition of store, to be a network of stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The kernel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diagnoses, simplified and prioritized. Ask: what is going on here? Judgement on facts. Simple story. Domain of action. Allows you to balance different guiding policies.
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At a minimum, a diagnosis names or classifies the situation, linking facts into patterns and suggesting that more attention be paid to some issues and less to others. An especially insightful diagnosis can transform one’s view of the situation, bringing a radically different perspective to bear. When a diagnosis classifies the situation as a certain type, it opens access to knowledge about how analogous situations were handled in the past. An explicit diagnosis permits one to evaluate the rest of the strategy. Additionally, making the diagnosis an explicit element of the strategy allows the rest of the strategy to be revisited and changed as circumstances change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guiding policy, how to overcome obstacles
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A guiding policy creates advantage by anticipating the actions and reactions of others, by reducing the complexity and ambiguity in the situation, by exploiting the leverage inherent in concentrating effort on a pivotal or decisive aspect of the situation, and by creating policies and actions that are coherent, each building on the other rather than canceling one another out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coherent actions, carry out the policy. Actions can’t be orthogonal, ie. Fords platform for cars, and acquiring multiple brands. Proximity objectives can help actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the kernel like a doctor diagnosing and prescribing a plan for a patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you fail to identify and analyze the obstacles, you don’t have a strategy. Instead, you have either a stretch goal, a budget, or a list of things you wish would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decentralized decision doesn’t work when costs or benefits don’t accrue to the decentralized players. Coordination is better only when gains are very large, otherwise decentralized is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A strategy is a way through a difficulty, an approach to overcoming an obstacle, a response to a challenge. If the challenge is not defined, it is difficult or impossible to assess the quality of the strategy. And if you cannot assess a strategy’s quality, you cannot reject a bad strategy or improve a good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leverage&quot;&gt;Leverage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leverage is context free. Leverage is not based on metrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threshold effects matter when there is a jump for value, like Advertising, or rolling out region by region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proximate-objectives&quot;&gt;Proximate objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eg: Landing on moon was a proximate objectives, dramatic leadership for US. JFK Laid out the steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proximate objectives help with trimming down the problem space. Making things tractable. Proximate objectives can cascade over org hierarchy and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weakest link matters when quantity cannot substitute for quality. Identify weakest links, sometimes incrementally is counter to progress in chain link systems. Sometimes central control helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premeditated
Anticipating 
Executing action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher performance required, the more in tune strategy must be, and the numbers of people that are required to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy must be designed, accounting for tradeoffs. Resources and actions yields an advantage in challenging situations. If you have less resources need better integration. Resources can be patents or relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy design must fit together, full supply chain, focus on what differentiates. Eg: Packard Trucks, Ikea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Must dig deeper on the strategy, leaders may not know, must formulate your own interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition and market forces are important to take a look at during strategy. Look at the 5 forces framework. In commodity businesses growth is not always a benefit (eg via acquisitions). Growth can not be engineered by acquisitions, only carefully designed strategic differentiators and a superior product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;using-advantages&quot;&gt;Using advantages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantages are in based in asymmetry, there are usually many, leaders need to identify which ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one has an advantage against everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need an isolating mechanism for Resources, either: reputation, patent, network effect, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive advantage is not something available to everyone (eg: training)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When listening to someone else, hear both less and more from What they are saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive advantage does not mean that you will succeed you must have some way to use the advantage to increase value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all competitive advantages translate into into an adjacent market. Knowledge does, brand can, relationships not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing demand based on limited supply is the oldest move in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-dynamics&quot;&gt;Using dynamics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exploit wave of change. Historical helps you calibrate how large the wave of change is. Must look at second order changes, derivative changes. Second order of TV was more Indy films that interested TV watchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you identify waves of changes, identify forces of change. For example microprocessors shifted things to software, ie Cisco and software networking. Many people saw it coming, but it’s why Japan conglomerates didn’t win, smaller upstarts did. Software REPL loop is faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guide-posts&quot;&gt;Guide posts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixed costs: largest competitors consolidate power. Kodak, IBM 
Deregulation: Subsidies Will benefit one customer takes over another, and most companies don’t understand this cost structure deeply.
Forecast biased: Rarely predict that growth peaks and then decline. Durable goods have this peak then replacement demand.
Incumbent response: protecting resource
Attractor State: future direction, based on overal efficiency (IP everywhere by Cisco), instead of corporate drive. Demonstrations: music == 2.5mb file. Newspapers, large bundled is no longer needed, aggregated, unbundled local news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inertia&quot;&gt;Inertia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entropy and inertia, entropy is outside. Inertia is the current business, culture, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Routine, ie: airlines and deregulation.
Culture: AT&amp;amp;T and Bell Labs, culture can crush ideas.
By proxy: profits drive this, slow customer adoption
Entropy: Organizational entropy is noticed when people are under managed. Management must control strategy design through organization, ie people moving into other orgs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nvidia. Clear strategy, fabless, SGI triangle based rendering - highly parrelellizable, sharp demand for faster 3D, CPU didn’t have the same speed scale. Was able to improve speed 3x faster than CPU cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;science-of-strategy&quot;&gt;Science of strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about your own thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy is a hypothesis, follow scientific method. not a crank winding exercise. Not a problem in deduction, problem of induction. What anomalies are we learning from. Anomalies are not found in nature, they are found in the eye of the observer in their perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starbucks started with a vision of a espresso bar, started iterating learning merged with the coffee bean company. Why did Starbucks win this instead of European industry? Incumbents saw Starbucks more as a coffee flavored milk company, with the confusing menu than a coffee shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Human intelligence is like a flashlight shining on one thing and something else goes dark&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of things to do now causes you to prioritize the intersection of action and importance. Pushes against our myopia. Andrew Carnegie and Taylor,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;List the 10 most important things to do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people grab the first problem or insight, however to dig into strategy you have to dig into the why. Why did you come up with that solution to a problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is natural to grab for the first solution, we don’t like ambiguity. In tough strategic discussions where there is no one correct solution, no one clear decision making formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In strategy, knowledge isn’t enough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tools for fighting myopia
The kernel
Instead of what happened, ask why did it happened.
Create / Destroy - internal panel of experts, can embody different people. What would Jobs say, Iger, Ahh, Dorsey, etc&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Question own judgment&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recording judgement&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-your-head&quot;&gt;Keep your head&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t follow the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sufficiently complex systems, are incomplete, have statements that can’t be proven true or false, must look outside of the system. Happens in systems based on popular opinion, for example, mortgages backed by government, and curriculums based on student polls&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/08/03/Good-strategy-bad-strategy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/08/03/Good-strategy-bad-strategy/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thinking In Bets</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Life is two things, quality decisions and luck.
Resulting bias: Weighting quality of decision to the outcome, ie. sane football call is criticized based on outcome. Related to hindsight bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We evolved to drive correlations from outcomes. Type 1 error, false positive, ie. rustling leaves in the wind meaning a tiger. Type 2 error, false negative could be fatal. System 1 reflexive, System 2, deliberate. We are wired to be defensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chess is a game of complete information, almost always a path to winning. Poker is incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lives are too short to use pure data to dig into decision quality. 4 count tosses vs 1000 to determine if coin is fair&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions are bets on the future, there is no right or wrong&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loss aversion bias: being wrong is 2x as painful as being right. We should question right decisions just like wrong ones. &lt;em&gt;There is always an opportunity cost.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All decisions are bets. Not going to a movie is a bet. Taking time off from work. Not all bets are zero sum, just like decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bets are only as good as our beliefs. We form beliefs easily, abstract belief formation based on language is unique to us. Truth seeking is damaging. Blind spot bias is worse if you’re smarter, because you can spin risk arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking simple question of: &lt;em&gt;Wanna bet?&lt;/em&gt; challenges this, pushes us back to assumptions of the belief. Note: uncertainty can be confrontational. Saying a probability with a statement invites uncertainty and can improve the statement or decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-gets-in-our-way&quot;&gt;What gets in our way?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big difference in getting experience and becoming an expert. 
belief &amp;gt; bet &amp;gt; outcome
Uncertainty hurts the learning loop, outcomes can be based on many things. Inferring cause from outcome is hard, eg: dr office and cough, is it cancer or not. Need to identify whether outcome was luck or skill. Outcomes alone can’t tell us decision quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fielding errors &lt;em&gt;is self serving bias&lt;/em&gt;, easy to blame bad outcomes on luck. This is how we process information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very hard to go from right to wrong, biases pull in either direction. &lt;em&gt;Attributing right to skill and wrong to luck is common. The reverse is related to depression.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zero sum games, we evolved to compete, adds fuel to self serving biases and we can easily project the outcomes. Accuracy and objectivity, give praise when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golden rule of habit, you have to deliver the same outcome. Boost to ego on attributing everything to skill, flipped for peers. Respect the habit loop, we strive for positive reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of a the good feeling or bad when admiring a mistake, what if it is missing a learning opportunity. Practice this routine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep the reward of feeling better than peers, but focus it on things like: give better credit, figure out where the decisions, etc. Ideally, we don’t judge or compare, like mindfulness teaches, do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if people challenged us every time we fielded an outcome into skill and luck, if we had to bet, we’d challenge. Thinking in bets compound learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treat outcome fielding as bets.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;groups&quot;&gt;Groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buddy system: Not all people want truth seeking, to be challenges. Who is in my “decision pod”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirmation thought vs exploratory thought within groups. Focus on accountability and accuracy over confirmation. Diversity helps here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a charger for the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social approval for accuracy. Easier to look for accuracy in positive outcomes, losing ones are hard. much of our biased decisioning has on the information or uncertainty that we may have, groups help with this, can’t know the truth without hearing the other side. Even just one or two dissenting ideas offers enough diversity of views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Betting markets are more efficient than experts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be a day sharer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don’t shoot the messenger, or think everyone is an idiot.&lt;/em&gt; Imagine if the message came from a much different source. We can analyze decisions before knowing outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Remembering the future”: Recruiting past and future version of myself to test decisions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temporal discounting, impulsiveness. If wet bring our future self into decisions we can combat this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideas-to-change-behavior&quot;&gt;Ideas to change behavior&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we could “pre-regret”. 10min10mon10year. Don’t be a ticket watcher of our own lives, like long term stock holding. Look back, would we remember this bad thing 1 year from now? If it happened a year ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision swear jar. Best, right, totally have it coming, luck, wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expected value multipliers based on confidence of outcome. Can go deeper in decision tree when decisions depend on each other. Scenario planning is like military reconnaissance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standing at the end and looking backwards is better than looking into the future. “Back casting” it’s like holding up a headline. Works where there is low probability decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Better net performance if you think of positive outcomes. But still explore negative outcomes (pre mortem)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/06/10/Thinking_In_Bets/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/06/10/Thinking_In_Bets/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Book of Why</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;No mathematical equations for Cause and Effect. Statistics pushed this aside, correlation is not causation. Path Analysis starts to help here. So does Casual Diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is dumb. Doesn’t tell us why. Causal modes can help machines tell us what they are doing and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Query, data, assumptions = inherence engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counterfactual are key to why. Data can not show cause and effect unless done by controller experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ladder-of-causation&quot;&gt;Ladder of causation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things we can imagine are the bedrock of causation (from Sapiens). Modularity, swapping variables and recalculating outcomes. Observe =&amp;gt; doing =&amp;gt; imagining. Last step is creating theories on cause / effect of tools for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ladder: 
Association. “What if I see”, regressions.
Intervention. “Changing what is”. A/B testing is one way. 
Counterfactual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causal models are much more resilient then probability distributions. Cause happens when intervention or imagination happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La-QAplases theorem, central limit theory, sum of random decisions will end up to a normal distribution. Price is Right balls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regression to mean is not a causal relationship. Ie sophomore slump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correlation coefficient detrrmines how two variables interact and of they revert to a mean, can plot these and look at slope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;causal-inference&quot;&gt;causal inference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khaneman: success = talent + luck. More success is a but more talent and lots of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correlation killed causation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causation is not to prove X means Y, or to define X by studying Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics is methods of reduction of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayesian thinking started to incorporate causal thinking. Prior Belief + New Evidence = Revised Belief&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bayesian-from-evidence-to-cause&quot;&gt;Bayesian from evidence to cause&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayesian networks are from cause to effect, or induction from evidence to hypothesis (and then cause).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief network propagation is implementation of baysian network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core idea is how much evidence do you need to go from probable to improbable, ie “dead people stay dead”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayes rule helps the scientific method in organic outcomes. Inverse probabilities are crazy, re mammograms and the psychological harm they can cause. Bayes is subjective, or if you have history of cancer percentage goes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bayes-networks-1&quot;&gt;Bayes networks 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Child to parent is updating with likelyhood ration. Parent to childen update with conditional probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inverse probabilities are the simplest Bayesian networks. Two boxes one connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditional independence. explain away syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chains, forks and Colliders. Explain away and collider bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sparse networks are necessary as baysian calculation grows at 2^n&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayesian networks are just probability tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrows in causal diagrams are outcomes of hypotheticals, if you can modify something and another changes then there is an arrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayesian networks allow you to test relations based on correlations in data,A-B, A-C, can test of any cortisone between A and C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;confounding-variables&quot;&gt;confounding variables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What should you control for? Mixing variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics has trouble with interventions or intention to do something, however this is key to causal relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Randomization solves for confounding variables. Confounding variables are discrepancies between p(X&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Y) and p(X do Y).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back door principle - removing any causal lines that affect X. Sometimes controlling for a variable a can make it a confounder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QAMoney and capatilism can super charge confounders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paradoxes&quot;&gt;Paradoxes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When causal expectations s collide with probabilistic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules of the game, or how we gain information is just as important as the days itself, re the Monty Hall problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causeless correlation is hard to imagine, Bayesian conditioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any hypothesis that survives a threat is more like, greater the threat, more likely it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to visualize Colliders, non intuitive. If you flip a coin 100 times, and only record when a coin is heads, you will have 75 rows, if you look at those rows, the other will almost always be tails - heads is the collider. Collider structures, the at we observe data. All good looking people are assholes, you’ve controlled on looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intervention&quot;&gt;intervention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to influence use the backdoor formula – Anki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front door formula, allows you to control for confounders the same way as RCT - Anki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;List out 3 rules. Great verifier but not solver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Path deletion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instrumental variables, alternative to front door formula. Must be independent from confounders. Path from Z to Y, and strong association between Z and X.  Should be randomized like genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;counterfactuals&quot;&gt;counterfactuals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see what could happen, all animals can see what is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counterfactuals give us language to break correlation. Rooster and sunrise, if no rooster, not no sunrise. or B would not have occurred if not for A. Most similar worlds, ie if you take aspirin headache goes away, except for other worlds where you bumped your head, but bumping my head is not similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structured causal models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logic void of representation is metaphysics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Kahneman found that people are more likely to undo a rare event than a common one, ie blaming a train that a train left on schedule versus leaving early. Also are more likely to undo events they caused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mediation&quot;&gt;Mediation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total vs direct vs indirect effects (which are counterfactuals)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct can be affected by confounders, indirect a mediator, weighed by unit relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linear modeling can not spot mediations in day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data may be intense, but the questions are simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data morning can help identify the questions we need to ask, then need a casual model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data interpretation requires hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transportability between different studies allows us to not look at differences in relations as a threat but as a way to grow the study. Do calculus allows this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai&quot;&gt;AI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule based &amp;gt; Bayesian &amp;gt; deep learning, CNNs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CNNs are empirical, opaque system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency and causal reasoning is necessary for clear communication, needs to understand counterfactuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should machines have the illusion of free will? Rationalization may be a post-hoc system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From HN:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the same kind of experiment. An experiment in the scientific sense tweaks the process that generates the data, not the interpretation of the data. There is an inspiration / hypothesis creation step between old data and new experiment.
Main differences: A hypothesis is sorta kinda like your model’s coefficients, but more generally applicable. And you have no feedback loop between model coefficients and input data.
So yeah, you are doing very sophisticated curve fitting. It is useful alright, it’s just not very much like science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Chomsky is saying is that the control variables don’t exist until you create them because the most telling things don’t happen until you have a specific hypothesis and make them happen to test the hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 10:10:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/06/02/Book_of_Why/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://willemsavenue.com/books/2018/06/02/Book_of_Why/</guid>
        
        <category>complete</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
